♪ [dramatic music] ♪
Dartmoor Prison
isolated from the outside world
by walls of granite
They say you can get out of here
by merely telling what you know
You may or may not be another
Scotland Yard bloke
but I'll give you the same
answer I gave the others
I still have two years, eight months
and six days left
in which to make musical boxes
that will be sold at auction for the
benefit of this delightful sanctuary
and I intend to sell them
♪ [music box] ♪
Move along
(male) And now we come
to the next object on our list
or I should say objects
because there are three of them
Now, ladies and gentlemen
these can be bought together or separately
Now these beautiful little musical boxes
only arrived this morning
and I didn't intend to put them
on the auction block until later
but I'm going to sell them now
So good friends
[inaudible] I've got news to say
Lend me your ears
And what do you hear?
♪ [music box] ♪
Right
The beautiful tinkle-tinkle
of a musical box
What a lovely trinket
what a beautiful gift
created and made by loving hands
A thing of beauty and utility
Now who's going to start me with £5?
It's a bargain, £5
Do I see any hands?
If a connoisseur in the house
will go £3 point
£2
£1
Ten shillings
Thank you, sir
Ladies and gentlemen
ten shillings is offered for a musical box
you couldn't buy anywhere in London
for less than £5
Bit of a steal to let it go
for ten shillings
Like taking milk from a baby
Alright, we still have the ten shillings
Ten shillings, ten shillings is offered
ten shillings is offered
Anybody going to give me £1?
Anybody £1?
Someone, somewhere give me a pound
A pound, £1 is offered
£1 is offered ladies and gentlemen
£1 is offered
Have we got a £2?
Have we got a £2, sir?
£2, £2 is offered
£2 is offered, going once
twice
third and the last call
sold to the gentleman for £2
Sorry, my dear
Now ladies and gentlemen
comes the opportunity to purchase
an exact duplicate
of the beautiful little musical box
just bought by this gentleman
for the ridiculous low price of £2
It's exactly the same
exactly the same, made with the same hands
You hear that? Isn't that lovely?
That tinkle tinkle tinkle tinkle
♪ (music box) ♪
Sounds like bells to me, you know,
with little angels pulling on the rope
Who'll give me £2 for it?
Who'll start me with £2 for it?
Will anyone start me with £2?
Oh, come, come, ladies and gentlemen
You know, from your enthusiasm
we might all be in Scotland
instead of London
Please buy it for me, Daddy
£2, certainly not
we all might be in Scotland
Besides I don't like these men
£1, ten shillings
£1, £1 is ours
£1, £1 is offered
£1 is offered, going £1
In the advance, we're once
going twice
the third and the last call
Sold to the lady for £1
Smart bidding, my dear
Thank you
We come to the third and last
of these beautiful little musical boxes
Exactly the same
tinkle-tinkle
Isn't that lovely?
Ladies and gentlemen, I don't bring
you here to golly you and swindle you
This is an exact replica
of those two I just sold before . . .
(knock)
We're closed
But this is extremely important
Come in, sir, come in
I'm sorry to disturb you
but I was unfortunately delayed
from arriving on time
to bid on certain articles
which I was rather anxious to obtain
Well, perhaps they weren't sold, sir
We are carrying several things over
Erm, what might the articles be, sir?
Three identical musical boxes
about, er, so large
Oh, I'm sorry, sir, but they were sold
Pity you weren't here to bid on them
They didn't bring anything
like the real value
I'm most anxious to obtain them
I wonder if your records would show
who the purchasers were
Oh, we usually don't give out
that information, sir
For certain, shall we say
sentimental reasons
I'm most anxious to get in touch
with the purchasers
I'd be willing to pay, shall we say
£5
Well for certain sentimental reasons, sir
we'd be very happy to oblige
Alfred! Today's sale
the three musical boxes
The musical boxes
Ah, here we are
The first purchase for £2
Mr. Julian Emery, 52 Fortman Square
Write these adresses down, Alfred
Yes, sir
Second didn't leave any name
How unfortunate
I think she's a dealer
You see, they don't like us to know
where they're things are going
On account of the profits
You say the second purchaser was a woman?
Can you give me a description of her?
Oh, she was a young woman
fairly tall, slender
a light complexion, and dark hair
and she was wearing a–
A grey suit, don't you remember?
That's right
She probably runs a gift shop
She paid £1
You say she comes here fairly frequently?
Oh, I didn't say so
but she does, sir
Like as not she'll come in on Thursday
We have sales on Mondays and Thursdays
Ah, and the third box?
The third, Mr. William Kilgour
143 B. Hampton Way
For ten shillings
Mmm, quite a drop from £2
Mr. Kilgour was a Scotchman
Oh, well, thank you
You're most helpful
Oh, thank you, sir!
And anytime you're passing, drop in
We always have lovely things for sale
Our card, sir
Thank you, I'll be back Thursday
The message reached us too late
The musical boxes are being sold
Let's get out of here
Someday you'll go too far
Reaching for a star, you fool
Yet a fool may touch a star
Col. Cavanaugh
if he reach high enough
But not posses it as you would
The musical boxes, they're being sold
What a pity for you, my dear Col.
Is it my fault that the message
reached us only an hour ago?
Is it my fault that they were sold?
She can't hold me responsible for that
I hope for your sake you're right
♪ [violin] ♪
They will call upon you tonight
at a quarter to eight
a gentlemen who desires to consult you
upon a matter of the very deepest moment
Ha! Do you remember that letter, Holmes?
It was written over two years ago
An interesting case
devilishly interesting
Irene Adler
What a striking looking woman
from the brief glance I had of her
seems only yesterday
What charm, what poise, and what a mind!
Sharp enough and brilliant enough
to outwit the
the great Sherlock Holmes himself
I take it the new issue
of the Strand Magazine is out
containing another of your
slightly lurid tales
It is indeed!
And what do you call this one?
I call it A Scandal In Bohemia
Not a bad title, eh?
Hmm.
If you must record my exploits
I do wish you'd put less emphasis
on the melodramatic
and more on the
intellectual issues involved
More on the intel . . .
What do you mean by that?
Well I do hope you'd given, uh
The Woman a soul
She had one you know
"The Woman"
I suppose you mean Irene Adler
Yes
I shall always remember her
as The Woman
(knock)
(Watson) Come in
Hey! Stinky
Fatso, old boy, how are you?
How are you, old boy?
Haven't seen you for years
I want you to meet my old friend
Sherlock Holmes
Holmes, this is Stinky
in other words, Julian Emery
How do you do, Mr. Emery?
Watson has often spoken of you
Oh, has he?
Yes, we were at school together
It was more years ago
than I care to remember
but you didn't come in here
just to remind me of that
No, I just happened to be
in the neighborhood and
saw your lights burning
so I took the liberty of looking you up
Still writing your mystery stuff?
Yes, there's a new one out this week
Good, I never miss 'em
Oh, good, thanks!
I say, that bandage
makes you look very interesting
still poking your nose into
other people's business as usual?
I haven't a value's notion
Somebody bopped me on the head
in my own living room
and then proceed to commit the most
idiotic burglary you ever heard of
Fellow must have been as barmy as a coot
Barmy, why?
Come sit down, old boy
You like a cup of tea?
Huh? Oh, alright
I'll go and [inaudible]
Why do you say the robbery
was idiotic, Mr. Emery?
Oh, simply for the fact that
with about £5000 worth of
musical boxes in my living room
the thief who I caught in the act
made off with one that isn't even worth £5
I gather you're a collector
of musical boxes
Yes, I am indeed
Some of them very beautiful
but not the one that was stolen
The thief evidently grabbed
the first thing that came to his hand
when he heard me coming into the room
Isn't it rather odd isn't it
that having disposed of you
he didn't pick up something more valuable?
Was there anything unusual about the stolen box?
No, nothing at all
I picked it up in the south of France
several years ago
You say you have many valuable music boxes
yet the thief made of with one
that isn't worth £5
Sounds like rather an intriguing
little problem
Well, I take it that
he was just an ordinary petty thief
and didn't know the value
That is a possible explanation
yet I venture to say
that the average petty thief
has a more extensive knowledge
of the value of objet dar
than the average collector
Well, anyway, that's gotten the odysary
They didn't get very excited about it
That's consistent, anyway
I wonder if I might see your collection
Mr. Emery
Oh, of course you could, yes
Nothing a collector likes more
than showing off his trophies
When would it suit you?
No time like the present
Good!
My place is just round in Portwood Square
-Shall we?
-Yes, right
Hello, where are you going?
Stinky hasn't had his tea yet
Oh, I'm sorry
We're going round to my place
where I'm going to give you something
better than tea
Now this one was made for Joey XV
and is one of the very few
still in existence in that period
and a particularly fine specimen at that
♪ (tweet) ♪
Charming isn't it?
Quite
They all sound to me like a lot of mice
running about on a tin roof
I'm afraid you have no ear
for music, Watson
Give me a good old band
playing a rousing march
you have all your
silly little tweet-tweets
♪ [whistling] ♪
[laughing]
Is this one…
♪ [music box] ♪
Stupid thing
Singing rabbit, humph
What would you say [inaudible] has a value
of a box like that, Mr. Emery?
Well, it's hard to say out of hand
but I was thinking of bringing
about five or six hundred pounds today
It's the gem of my collection
Yet a thief who steals an oddity
like a musical box
passes up one worth £500
for one of almost no value at all
Odd
Very odd
What was the stolen box like, Mr. Emery?
Oh, just a plain wooden box
about, em, so big
Mmmhmm
As a matter of fact I have one over here
almost exactly like it
I picked this up yesterday
at an auction room in Nightsbridge
♪ [music box] ♪
Payed only £2 for it
Course I wouldn't ordinarily
add one like this to my collection
but the, em, the tuning freed me
I had never heard it before
♪ [whistling] ♪
You have a remarkable ear
for music, Holmes
Rather an unusual melody
–Sit down, will you
–Thanks
You say you bought that box
at an auction sale yesterday
Yes, the Gaylord auction rooms
in Nightsbridge
run by old, what's his name
Crabtree
That's the man
At what time was the robbery committed?
About 3:00 this morning
You know, Mr. Emery
that box in the robbery
might well be cause and effect
especially since you say
that the stolen box
accurately resembles this one a great deal
and Scotland Yard
were not particularly interested, eh?
Oh, yes, well that
I wouldn't blame them for that
especially as I told them
I was quite unable to describe the thief
except of course for the fact that
it was definitely a man
All you remember is that you came in here
and someone struck you on the head
Yes, and the next thing I knew
my man was trying to revive me
It might be wise for you
to put that box away somewhere
lock it up
Oh, I don't think that's necessary
Besides everything's insured
Well, at least if any further attempts
at robbery are made
I'd suggest that you call the police
rather than running into
any possible danger
Oh, come Holmes
aren't you being a bit of an alarmist?
Possibly
I must agree with old Stinky
it seems to me you are making
rather a mountain out of a moleskin
"Molehill" is the word, old boy
and it's time you were in bed
(laughter)
Thanks so much
for letting us see your place
No, it's very good meeting you
Holmes, I can't understand
why you were so mysterious
Seems to me the petty thief explanation
was the only sensible one
Really?
I can't see how you could believe
it was anything else
I didn't say I believed it
to be anything else
The petty thief theory is the
obvious one, I grant you
However, it's often a mistake
to accept something as true
merely because it's obvious
The truth is only arrived at
by the painstaking process
of eliminating the untrue
We are not able to do that in this case
without further data
Rubbish, you're pulling my leg
You're trying to turn a
a [inaudible] robbery
into an international plot
No, I'm not
And I just hope that your friend Stinky's
a little more cautious in the future
just in case
[telephone]
Hello
Yeah?
Julian Emery here
Who?
Of course I remember you, Mrs. Courtney
Yes, you are the one bright spot
at the boringly dull affair of [inaudible]
Huh?
Of course it isn't too late to come around
Yes, I shall be
delighted to give you a drink
I'll tell you what, come straight up
and I'll be at the door [inaudible]
Alright, fifteen minutes? Good
I shall be counting each moment
No, I mean that really
Right, goodbye
♪ [humming] ♪
Boo!
Oh! You startled me
(laughing) Did I?
Must be the pixie in me
I know I shouldn't have called you so late
but I was at a party
just around the corner
and I remembered your invitation
to see your collection of musical boxes
My dear Mrs. Courtney
the pleasure is all the greater
for being so unexpected
My friends call me Hilda
Mine call me Stinky
Stinky, how quaint
What a perfectly wonderful
collection of musical boxes!
You know, when you told me
you had a collection
I had no idea it was so attractive
They appeal to the ear
as well as to the eye
Oh, what a plain little one
Why it looks just like a country cousin
amid all this grandeur
No, no, no, no, you mustn't
underestimate the country cousin
Only last night a burglar broke in here
And with all these to choose from
went after the one very much like it
Really?
Yes, I don't mind
the loss of the box so much
but I do resent this crack on the skull
But it makes you look so interesting
Do you think so?
Uh-huh
That's funny, that's what old Fatso said
Fatso?
I mean Dr. Watson
He was here this evening with a friend
A Mr. Holmes
He's interested in my collection too
Sherlock Holmes?
Yes, do you know him?
I've heard of him
He seems to think I'm in some sort of, uh
danger
What a haunting tune!
It takes me right back to my childhood
Really?
See that's odd that you should be
interested in that particular musical box
Odd, why?
'Cause Mr. Holmes is also interested in it
He may have been more
interested in the tune than in the box
By Gilders, that's right
I remember now
He whistled it note for note
having only heard it once
Really?
He must be a remarkable man
Bit of an alarmist if you ask me
Don't you believe in warnings?
Course not
Who'd want a box like that?
I would
You're not serious?
Oh, but I am
You put me at a very awkward position
I'm a collector, you know
and a collector buys but never sells
But, if the price were high enough
Price has nothing to do with it
It's the principle of the thing
Yes, well, we haven't had our drink
No thanks, I must be getting along
Must you really?
I'm afraid so
You're not walking out on me, are you?
My reputation, Stinky
I say, you know
you are an attractive woman
Thanks
♪ [intense music] ♪
You fool
I told you to wait outside
What did you have to kill him for?
All I had to do was walk out with this
He held you in his arms
Don't touch him
Don't touch anything
Now get out!
I'm sorry
You're sorry?
What about me?
This is murder
What about Scotland Yard?
What about Sherlock Holmes?
Now get out!
Did you get it?
Good
Did you have any trouble with it?
Just a matter of murder
Ah, Mr. Holmes
Hopkins
Thanks for coming so promptly
Inspector Lestrade suggested
that I call through to you
Mr. Emery was a client
of Mr. Holmes, Inspector
Indeed?
You didn't mention that
when I telephoned you, Mr Holmes
Well, not exactly a client, Inspector
Sgt. Thompson
He was killed between the hours of 11
and 2:00 this morning, Mr Holmes
Must of been someone he knew
or someone of whom he had no suspicion
Poor old Stinky
It's all my fault
I should have prevented this
Well, it's no time to start
talking about that now, Dr.
Apparently it's gone
That's the second attempt on the musical
box that Emery bought at the auction sale
and this time it was succesful
But that box was only worth £2
It was worth a man's life, Watson
I think we better pay a visit
to Gaylord's auction room
and that fellow Crabtree
Inspector, may I suggest that you make
a complete search of this flat
for a small plain musical box
about that size
Thank you, come on, Watson
You say the first box
went to Mr. Julian Emery
the second Mr. Kilgour 143 B. Hampton Way
the third to the unidentified young lady
who presumably has a shop
and lives near Gilder's Green
That's right Mr. Holmes
Isn't it rather strange Mr. Crabtree
that you used to have three identical
musical boxes all playing the same tune
Where did they come from?
Dartmoor Prison
Dartmoor?
We get a regular shipment
from there every month
The inmates manufacture them
Well, they make all kinds
of things, you know
pipe racks, waste paper baskets
musical boxes-
Did you happen to notice
if anyone showed any particular interest
during the auction
and the purchases of these three boxes?
Oh, come now, Mr. Crabtree
this is very literally
a matter of life and death
Well, since you put it that way
Mr. Holmes
There was a gentleman came in here
about an hour after closing time
and he was in an awful state, he was
He gave me £5 to tell him
where the boxes had gone to
He said they had
a sentimental value for him, sir
Hmm, explains his sentiment
Can you describe him?
He was tall, distinguished looking
and he had
grey hair and a mustache
He was quite a gentleman, sir
And what was his reaction
when you were unable to supply him
with the address of the young lady
who owned the shop?
I told him the young lady
usually come back on Thursday
He said he'd come back on Thursday
and that's tomorrow
Thank you Mr. Crabtree
you've been very helpful
Thank you!
Come along, Watson
Where are we going now, home?
Well, I'm going to Mr. Kilgour
the man who bought the third box
(buzz)
But hang it all, Holmes
How do you know those other two
musical boxes are of any importance?
I don't, but I certainly have no intention
of waiting till the owners
are murdered to find out
(buzz)
No one at home
I hope that's the explanation
Well, have a look through this window
Doesn't seem to be anyone there
The whole place seems deserted
as far as I can see
Yes
Mr. and Mrs. Kilgour at home?
No
When do you expect them?
Oh, in an hour or so
There's no use [inaudible]ing about
They don't buy nothing from peddlers
Peddlers! My good woman
this is Mr. Sherlock Holmes
Sherlock Holmes? Oh, go on
You mind if we come in and wait?
My business is rather urgent
Well, I got to go out and do me shopping
and I don't know if Mrs. Kilgour
would like any strangers nosing about
Quite all right, I assure you
Well, I've got to be off
You two wait in the parlor
and no smoking either
Mrs. Kilgour says it smells up the 'ouse
Funny old girl, Holmes
Hmm
Park Place
Park Lane
and what would the likes of you
be doing in Park Lane?
Now don't worry about the theatre
if you know how to get to
Park Lane, off it
You know, Holmes, I've been thinking
There must have been something
hidden in that box of old Stinky's
stolen jewelry, possibly
What's up, Holmes?
Listen
[knocking]
That's just the steam in the water pipes
Watson!
Great Scott!
Come on, Holmes
get her on the chair here
It's all right, my dear
There, there, there
Now don't worry
It's all over
There you are, dear, don't cry any more
She tied me up and shut me in the cupboard
I know, I know
She won't come back
Did you show her your new musical box?
Yes, she said she wanted to hear it play
and as soon as I showed it to her
she grabbed on-
I know, I know, I know, now don't worry
We'll buy you a new musical box
Yes my dear, the best one in London
Watson
Oh, what a fool, what a fool I've been
What do you mean, Holmes?
She took the musical box out of this house
in that market basket
right under our very noses
Why, do you think the Kilgour char woman
would want to take the music box?
She isn't the Kilgour char woman
She's a considered actress
An extremely clever, unscrupulous woman
who will stop at nothing
Take care of the child, will you
till her parents get back
Explain everything to them
Of course I will
Holmes! Where are you going?
Somewhere, somehow
I must get to the young lady
who bought that third musical box
before our opponents find her
I only hope that I won't be too late
Oh no, no no no darling, you
you mustn't cry anymore
Now, cheer up
Would you like to hear old Uncle
make a noise like a duck?
[quacking]
Oh, sorry
♪ [music box] ♪
Now, ladies and gentlemen
how much am I offered for this beautiful
lace dressed in china figurine?
A lady of the French court
Now this is the genuine article
What a beautiful ornament
for your mantlepiece
or you could use it as a centerpiece
on the dining room table
Now, will somebody start me for £10?
Somebody start me for £10?
£8
£7
Alright 5, £5 is offered
£5 is offered, £5 is offered
£5.10, £5.15, £5.15
£6 is offered, £6, £6
going once
going twice
the third and the last call
we'll be all done
Sold to the lady from twig for £6
Next we have a real museum piece
ladies and gentlemen
a fine nineteenth century doll
a costume and exact replica
of the holiday clothes
worn by the Hungarian peasant women
Now, ladies and gentlemen
an item like this could cost you
from £15-20 in a western shop
I'm not going to ask
for anything like that
Who'll give me £2 for it?
£2, anybody offering me £2?
£2 for the Hungarian, £2-
£1, 1?
Anybody give me £1?
Anybody offer me £1 for the doll?
£1 is offered, ladies and gentlemen
£1 is offered
Now, I'm not going to waste
your valuable time
or mine, in trying to get half of
what this beautiful doll is worth
The young lady can steal it for £1
and that's her good fortune
So it's going once
It's going twice, the third and last call
Anymore?
Sold to the young lady for £1
And now, ladies and gentlemen
may I draw your attention to something
which may be a great surprise to you
worthy of any collection
The only other one like it
is in the British museum
It's a Ming vase of the seventh dynasty
This vase lay in a large collection
somewhere outside Rome for over
two centuries as I understand it
It was discovered there by the Notre Dandy
Crilliams and Andrew Carperson
Now some of you may remember
Sir Andrew Carperson
besides being a noted traveler and
antiquarian he's also a gentlemen writer
The girl with a parcel
in her hands, that's her
Are you sure that's the girl?
Well, she fits definitely
the auctioneer's description
Follow her, Hamid
It's lovely, dear
And only £1
We can get at least three for it
Easily
I'll go make some tea
I could do with a cup
Right
(bell)
Good afternoon
I'm looking for a birthday gift
for a seven year old girl
What would you suggest?
We have some lovely dolls
Now this Hungarian peasant-
I think she has enough dolls already
Books are always welcome
Well, I'm looking for something
a little different
Now, that's rather cute
What is it?
Oh, that's a musical box
Children always love them
and this is an exceptionally nice one
It plays many tunes
♪ (music box) ♪
Have you any others?
Yes
If you'll just step this way
I have only two left
♪ (music box) ♪
My, my!
Are you sure this is all you have?
I'm sorry
they're rather hard to find, you know
That's our entire allotment
I did have one other
but I sold it earlier this afternoon
But it was only a plain wooden one
It wouldn't have been
a very nice gift for a child
Really?
Do you happen to know
who the purchaser was?
Why yes
He left his card
just in case anyone should inquire for him
How interesting
I'm sorry, but I'm afraid
I'll have to look a bit further
Thank you anyway
Good afternoon, thank you
(bell)
Cabby!
Follow that cab
Here now, right
Scotland Yard
Hop in
Sherlock Holmes
I might have known
We thought we were the hunters
instead of which we are the hunted
We've been fooled
We played right into his hands
Of course
He's had us followed
Don't look
The man in front of the toy shop
Hamin
Turn sharp right at the next corner
and again at the next
No photograph of her, Comissioner
as I expected
She's not a known criminal
But how do you expect to know her
if you do find her?
After all she was disguised
as a char-woman
Don't worry, old fellow
If I ever see her again I'll recognize her
Well, it won't be long till we know
who they are and from where they operate
Who's covering them?
Sgt. Thompson's following them, sir
They won't get away from him
He's a good man
We could have arrested them
at Tibert's Toy shop if we had any proof
But we know that they killed Emery
Proof, my dear fellow
We must have proof
We have x-rayed it, sir
There's nothing whatever
concealed in the box
We'll have a look at the plates
Hmm
There must be some clue
It'll probably be so obvious
that we've all overlooked it
Seems to me
we're up against a bunch of lunatics
Not lunatic's, my dear fellow
Extremely astute cold-blooded murderers
What could these little musical boxes
have in them that's so important
Don't forget they were made
in Dartmoor Prison
You can smuggle stuff into prison
but not out
You want us to break the box apart, sir
to see if the there's anything
the x-ray hasn't caught?
No, not yet
Do you mind if I take it?
Certainly
Thanks
The governor of Dartmoor Prison
informed us, sir
in answer to Mr. Holmes question
that all three musical boxes
were made by the same convict
John Davidson
Serving a seven year term, sir
Davidson? The Bank of England plate?
That will be all
Yes, sir
Now we're getting somewhere
If– wait a minute
How did you know
about the plates, Mr. Holmes?
I'm a student of crime, Inspector
I make it my business
to know about such things
and when the name
of Davidson was mentioned–
Who was this fellow, Davidson?
As long as Mr. Holmes seems to know
all about it already
I suppose there's no harm in telling you
Uh, two years ago in London
there occurred a robbery
of such tremendous importance
although the stolen articles
have no intrinsic value whatsoever
but the home secretary was instrumental
in seeing that not a word of it appeared
in any newspaper
But you never told me
anything about this, Holmes
You were away at the time
Articles of no intrinsic value
and yet of such importance?
Hmph, I don't understand
Davidson was aprehended
within fifteen minutes of committing the theft
but by that time
he had hidden the articles in question
and they've yet to be found
Before going further, Dr. Watson
I must inform you that this matter's not
to be mentioned outside of this room
Course not
Do I look like a man who gossips?
Let's not go into that now
old fellow, shall we?
Davidson had been employed
for years
in a position of extreme trust
by the engravings department
of the Bank of England
The articles he stole were nothing less
then a complete set of duplicate plates
for printing £5 notes
What?
The Bank of England's own plates?
Precisely
and with those plates a gang of crooks
could flood England with £5 notes
not forged in the usual sense of the word
but notes undetectable
from genuine Bank of England notes
in any way whatsoever
Good heavens
Any whisper at all
might have resulted in enormous damage
in shaking public confidence
in the treasury
We tried everything
after we had arrested Davidson
Offered him a shorter sentence
if he'd tell us where he'd hidden the plate
Why we even put in
Scotland Yard men with him as cell mates
but, no result
Obviously Davidson is a man
of strong character and infinite patience
Yet suddenly he feels impelled
to smuggle out the secret
of the hiding place of the plates
to his confederates
Why?
I don't understand, Mr. Holmes
Well, for example
had the Bank of England made any plans
to radically change
the design of the £5 notes
so that in say, uh
seven years from now
notes made from the stolen plates
would be worthless?
Confidentially , Mr. Holmes
such a move was discussed
but replacing all the £5 notes
in circulation
would be such a Herculean task that
nothing's been done about it as yet
I see
Of course there is another
possible explanation
Davidson didn't have much time to find
a hiding place before he was captured
He may be afraid
that the plates will be accidentally
discovered before he is released
hence his anxiety
to communicate their whereabouts
to his confederates as soon as possible
I believe you've hit it, Mr. Holmes
I'm sure that the message
is contained in this musical box
Or rather in all three musical boxes
since possession of all three
seems to be essential
Our opponents have 2/3 of the puzzle
and we have 1/3
Oh, what are you going to do, Holmes?
Try to deduce the methods
from the 1/3 that we have
♪ (music box) ♪
(whistling)
It's the same tune as the one
played by Emery's musical box
and yet it's different
Sounds the same to me
The tune
Somehow the tune
is the key to the mystery
It must be the tune
otherwise why use three musical boxes
to convey the message?
Why not collar boxes or shoe boxes?
(telephone)
Yes
Oh
It's for you, Inspector
Oh, thank you, sir
Inspector Hopkins speaking
What?
Where?
Gilder's Green station reports
they've just found Sgt. Thompson's body
There were tire marks on his clothes
He was
apparently run over by a taxi
What an unfortunate accident
Not an accident, my dear fellow
I'm afraid it's murder
♪ Oh, you never know
just who you're going to meet ♪
♪ When you're walking
down every London street ♪
♪ Mrs Orchid or Mrs Brown
Any subject of the crown ♪
♪ Oh, you never know
just who you're going to meet ♪
♪ Oh, you better hold your copper
in your 'and ♪
♪ Just in case you meet a lady
on the strand ♪
♪ Girls will think you're kind of sweet
And your day will be complete ♪
♪ Oh, you never know
just who you're going to meet ♪
♪ Now a gentlemen is judged
by 'is appearance ♪
♪ Yes a gentlemen is judged
by how he talks ♪
♪ Now he's much better off
When he's beckoned like a cough ♪
♪ Especially if he's takin' him
a walk ♪
What on earth is this outlandish place?
A rendezvous practice
Actors?
Buskers, old boy
You've seen them a thousand times
Actors only tame the queues
waiting outside theaters
♪ Oh, you never know
just who you're going to meet ♪
♪ When you're walking
down every London street ♪
♪ So you better wear your best
Go inside and look your best ♪
♪ Oh, you never know
just who you're going to meet ♪
♪ Oh, you better keep your manners
ripe and new ♪
♪ Just in case a lady
gives a howdy do ♪
♪ If your coat is in a fleet
Shine your shoes and keep them neat ♪
♪ Oh, you never know
just who you're going to meet ♪
Blimey
Mr. 'olmes
How are you, Joe?
Never better
And yourself?
Fine, thank you
I want you to meet a friend of mine
Dr. Watson, Joseph Cisto
Oh, well, any friend of Mr. 'olmes
is a friend of mine
Hi, Joe
You gave me a good turn once
that I'll never forget
Yes, I cleared Joe
of a most unpleasant charge
Murder, no less
Murder?
By proving to the satisfaction
of the police that he was busy at the time
blowing open someone's safe
That's right, governor
Good gracious me
And you're all well?
Now you can help me
Come on, buzz off, buzz off
Come on, stop it, stop it!
Can't a gentlemen have some
piece and quiet around 'ere?
And you too
There you are, Mr. 'olmes
Now we can have
some piece and quiet around 'ere
Thank you, Joe
There's £5 in this for you
Well, I wouldn't want
to take it on me-self, sir
but I can get someone
to do it for you for 'alf o'that
You don't know what the job is yet
For £5?
Murder aint it?
What?
No not murder, just
um, music
I want you to identify a song for me
Oh, there aint a song that's been written
that I don't know
That's why I came to you
Of course, the violin
is more my instrument, but, um
Oh, well
Here we go
Now listen to this, Joe
♪ (piano) ♪
Wait a minute
You're playing that wrong
That should be E♮ not E♭
You know the song?
Oh, yes, it's an old
Australian song called, uh
The Swagman
but you're playing it all wrong
That's what I hoped you'd say
Now listen again, Joe
♪ (piano) ♪
That's the same tune, all right
but you're making different mistakes
than you did the first time
No not mistakes, Joe, call them variations
Here, play the song for me, will you
the way it's written?
♪ (piano) ♪
There you are
Thank you, Joe
What's it mean, Holmes?
Are you onto something?
Perhaps
I don't know yet
It's probably a code of some sort
Joe!
Could you write the song sown for me
the way it was originally written?
Oh, sure, Mr. 'olmes
but it will take a few minutes
Mmmhmm
Here, Madel!
Pale ale
Come on, 'op to it, 'long with it
♪ (piano) ♪
Well, obviously it isn't the lyrics
No combination of those words
made any sense at all
The variations in the way
Emery's musical box played the tune
are different than the variations
in the one we have
You sure?
Quite
You see, I took the trouble to memorize
the tune as played by Emery's box
that night we were with him in his flat
Holmes, you amaze me
Did I mention, my dear fellow
one of the first principles
in solving crime
is never to disregard anything
no matter how trivial
Why are there three boxes?
Why not one?
Because the message
was obviously too long to be conveyed
by any one variation
Then there's the third box
The one that woman took from the Kilgours
That contains yet another
set of variations
Yes, well, it's all beyond me
Well, all we have to do now
is to plant the secret of the variations
Not a very easy problem to solve
my dear fellow
♪ (exciting music) ♪
Hello
What's up?
We've had company
I say, this is outrageous!
Ask Mrs. Hudson to come in here, will you?
Right
♪ (intense music) ♪
Mrs. Hudson!
Yes?
Oh, there you are
Will you come up here at once, please?
Coming, sir
Mercy me, Mr. Holmes
What has happened?
Who called while we were out, Mrs. Hudson?
Just a young lady
The one who said you wanted her
to wait for you
and a nice little old gentlemen with her
Our friends again, Watson
Friends?
What did the young lady look like?
Oh, I-I couldn't see hers face
She had a
a heavy black veil on
but she had such a nice way with her
Oh, I'm sorry Mr. Holmes
if I've done anything wrong
but you did say that I should always
let clients come in and wait for you
Don't worry, Mrs. Hudson, don't worry
You had no way of knowing
It's quite all right, quite all right
Now don't worry, Mrs. Hudson
Don't worry?
Where on earth's the musical box?
They didn't get it
Didn't get it?
Where is it?
It's in your hand
Huh?
That biscuit jar
Take the biscuits off the top
Now put your hand inside
and you'll find the music box
Well done, Holmes
Well done, amazing!
♪ (music box) ♪
Pff, nice fresh smell
Like a pub after closing time, pff
Mr. Holmes
What?
It's morning
Allow me to congratulate you
on a brilliant bit of deduction
It's not a transposition
not a polygraph transposition
not a trigraph
nor any known form of decoding
How about the Morse Code
have you tried that?
Yes, at about three o'clock this morning
I'm sorry, old man
I was only trying to help
♪ (violin) ♪
Oh, do me a favor
not again
Must have heard that thing
a thousand times
kept me awake all night
♪ (pizzicato violin) ♪
Not a very distinguished composition
I grant you
You know perfectly well
I don't know one tune from the other
When I was a kid, my people tried
to have me taught the piano
I always felt sorry
for that old teacher of mine
Poor old girl, finally reached a point of
numbering the keys for me
1, 2, 3, 4- even then
I-I never progressed beyond-
Numbering the keys, Watson!
The nineteenth key of the keyboard
is the nineteenth letter of the alphabet
Yes! Here
I'm done, I'll give it to you
old fellow, will you
The first altered note, write yes first
Now the eighth, the key
is H
The fifth key, E
The twelfth key
L
The sixth key, F
S-H-E-L-F
Shelf
Your piano lessons
were not in vain, old fellow
You've solved it
Thank you
Thanks, old man, ha!
We now have two thirds of the message
"Behind books"
"Third shelf"
"Secretary"
"Doctor S"
Presumably
these are the first and second
portions of the message
And this gang has the first
and third parts of it
Precisely
Then it's a stalemate
Yes, Commissioner
but we can't leave it like that
There's no doubt in my mind
that they'll try to secure
our third of the message that's missing
I assume you've taken every precaution
to guard the third music box
Oh, yes, it's carefully hidden at Baker St
with Dr. Watson on guard, however
I'm reasonably certain that, uh
difficult as it may be
we can find the plates
even without the missing part
of the message
"Behind books, third shelf
secretary, doctor S"
Outside of the fact that Davidson hid
the Bank of England plates
somewhere in London, Mr. Holmes
I don't see that we could rest at all
Allow me to point out to you, sir
the key words
"Doctor S"
It looks as though the plates were hidden
in the house of a doctor
Whether the "S" stands
for his first or last initial
remains to be determined
by a process of elimination
Frill, there must be ten thousand
doctors in London with
"S" for a first or last initial
Precisely
and every one of them
will have to be questioned in person
That's why I say
this is a task for Scotland Yard
It's a task all right
but Scotland Yard has searched worse
haystacks and found a needle
Well, for the time being
I'll leave the matter
in your hands, gentlemen
We'll call you if and when
we get a lead on our
mysterious "Doctor S"
In the meantime I intend to follow up
a little clue concerning a cigarette
Mmm
You are certain of the identification
of the tobacco?
Absolutely
I have made up this special blend
for only three customers
It is almost pure Egyptian
Mmmhmm
with a mixture of Laticia
for added body
and a pinch of Parich
merely a whisper as one might say
for elusive fragrance–
Yes yes, and the, um, the three customers?
Major Wilson in Bombay, India
Mmmhmm
Mrs. Catherine Leenington Smith
in Ireland
Yes, and the third?
Mrs. Hilga Courtney
of Park Mansions
Bryanston Square
Thank you
Thank you very much
you've been most helpful
It's a pleasure to have
been of service, Mr. Holmes
(buzz)
Yes
Mrs. Courtney
My name is Sherlock Holmes
Oh, do come in
Thank you
I've heard of you, of course, Mr. Holmes
I believe we have a mutual friend
in Sir Edward Brookdale
He's spoken to me of you quite often
Indeed?
And to what good fortune
am I indebted for this visit?
I think you know, Mrs. Courtney
Well, I did get a summons
for speeding last week
but outside of that I don't think I'm
of any interest to the police
Oh, come now, Mrs. Courtney
you seem to forget
that you and I have met before
I'm sorry
I'm sure I would have remembered
meeting the great Sherlock Holmes
Please sit down
Thank you
You say we met before
Yes
At the home of Mr. and Mrs. Kilgour
143 B. Hampton Rd
Kilgour
I don't think I know anyone of that name
Well, I didn't say you knew them
As a matter of fact you called on them
when they were out
I don't understand, Mr. Holmes
Really?
And you were dressed rather differently
Indeed
Cigarette?
Thank you
You know, Mrs. Courtney
people generally forget
you're assuming a disguise
but the shape of the ear
is an almost infallible means
of recognition and identification
to the trained eye
Evidently you've mistaken me
for someone else
Oh, no, not at all
though naturally I expected your denial
But when you payed your visit
to my rooms at Baker St
You carelessly left behind
another identification
I don't eglartha
Yes, I must admit they are
You see Mr. Holmes
to catch one as clever as you
I had to use a very special lure
I knew you'd be unable
to resist the bait of my cigarette
Having read with great interest
your monograph
On the Ashes of 140
Different Varieties of Tobacco
I should advise you
not to move, Mr. Holmes
I must congratulate you
on your ingenuity, Mrs. Courtney
It was indeed a brilliantly designed trap
Thank you, Mr. Holmes
Praise from a master is indeed gratifying
I shall always cherish the memory
of your flattering words
Memory?
Precisely
I'm afraid these gentlemen
have a most regrettable task to perform
Unless of course
you care to turn over
the missing musical box
with your pledge to take
no action against us in the future
I'm afraid that will be impossible
I thought that would be your answer
Hamid!
Careful!
Careful
There's no need to be so unnecessarily
rough with our distinguished guest
You realize, Mr. Holmes, that your demise
will not take place here, the, uh
corpus delectae, you know
Well, naturally
Shall we go?
So fearfully awkward
having a dead body lying about
Don't you agree, Mr. Holmes?
Another dead body
should not weigh too heavily
on your conscience, Mrs. Courtney
You mind if I have a cigarette?
Well, I don't see why not
♪ (dramatic music) ♪
(tire screech)
Be careful, Hamid!
It's the brakes, they bind
Thank you, Col. Cavanaugh
That's very considerate of you
♪ (dramatic music) ♪
You'll be happy to know, Mr. Holmes
that your death will be a painless one
Hamid
Attach this to the motor of the taxi
That little attachment, my dear Mr. Holmes
contains the deadly fluid know as
mono sulfride
The German's use it
with gratifying results in removing their
undesirables
♪ (dramatic music) ♪
Start the motor
(engine start)
Tape his mouth
Now, up with him, Hamid
You find yourself like
Mohamed's coffin, Mr. Holmes
Suspended between heaven
and earth
Plenty of fuel in the tank?
Good
It would be too bad to have anything
go wrong through so
simple an oversight
Come on
♪ (dramatic music) ♪
(coughing)
(knock)
Yeah, who's there?
(yawn)
Good afternoon
Mr. Sherlock Holmes
No, I'm Dr. Watson
Oh, of course, Dr. Watson
How stupid of me?
Not at all
Stupid of me
Won't you come in?
Well, I-I really came to see Mr. Holmes
Oh, I'm afraid he's out
I don't know when he'll be back
Perhaps there's something I can do
Won't you sit down?
Thank you
You know
Sherlock Holmes and I have been engaged
on a great many cases
Oh, really?
Yes, indeed
As a matter of fact, at this very moment
we're involved in one of the most baffling–
Well, oh, won't you tell me your trouble?
I may be able to help you
Very kind of you, Dr. Watson
perhaps
if I wouldn't be imposing too much
Imposing? Oh, there's no imposition
no imposition at all
A pleasure I assure you, now
tell me all about it Miss, uh
Miss Williams
Mrs. Williams
I live in Therough, Dr. Watson
and-and I've come up to London
in sheer desperation
my only sister has disappeared
and the local police seem utterly
unable to find her
Well, Holmes and I solved a case
exactly like that once
very interesting as far as I remember
I call it The Adventure of
the Solitary Cyclist
Oh, sorry
Now come to think of it
it wasn't so very similar
Entirely different
Couldn't think what I was saying
Where were we?
She's only seventeen, Dr. Watson, and
until she disappeared last Thursday she
seemed to be in the best of spirits
Possibly a romantic entanglement?
Oh, no, no, nothing of the sort
She left no note
didn't even pack a bag, no explanation
She just started to walk to the village
from our house in broad daylight and
simply vanished from the face of the earth
Oh, there, there, there, there
Might I have a glass of water?
Of course, a glass of water
One minute
♪ (dramatic music) ♪
There you are, my dear
Thank you, Dr. Watson
There, there, you're not to cry anymore
You must pull yourself together
I feel much better already
knowing that you're going to help me
Oh, Dr. Watson, look!
Good heavens!
(coughing)
Get through, get through
the fire brigade quickly
♪ (dramatic music) ♪
Haven't you a fire extinguisher?
By George, we have, in the kitchen
Don't you worry, Miss Williams
we'll have this thing out in no time
(coughing)
Ah, that's better
Get some air
There you see there was
there was no need
for the fire brigade after all
I hope you weren't too frightened
Miss Williams
Gone
That's the trouble with women
They always lose their heads
in an emergency
Hmph
The musical box!
Great Scott!
Miss Williams!
Well?
Good
And Holmes?
By now Mr. Holmes has no doubt
exchanged his violin for a harp
Well, that's assuming
that heaven is his destination
And now that we have
the missing musical box
♪ (music box) ♪
19th note
19th letter
"S"
He hasn't been there, you say
Holmes, where on earth have you been?
I've been trying to get you at the club
Scotland Yard, all over London
You were looking for me
in the wrong places
Holmes, a terrible thing's happened
I've been duped
That woman
she made a complete fool of me
Well, what do you mean?
Well, she came here
let off a smoke bomb
I thought the whole place was on fire
and my first thought was to
to save the musical box
No need to say anymore
She has the box
Yes
Don't blame yourself too much, old fellow
She is an extremely clever antagonist
Smoke bomb, you said?
(laughing)
Well, you can console yourself
with the thought
that your charming friend is
at least a reader of yours
What do you mean?
If I remember correctly
you wrote about my little experiment
with the smoke and the cry of fire
in the story you entitled
A Scandal in Bohemia which has just
appeared in the Strand Magazine
Alright, alright, old boy
Don't rub it in
Well, it may cheer you up to know
that she made a fool of me, too
That cigarette stub
It was planted here
for one express purpose
You got any bandaging around this place?
Bandaging, what's the matter, Holmes?
Are you hurt?
The explanations
will have to wait until later
At the moment we are faced with a problem
which I fear is insurmountable
Come over here a moment, would you?
Right
Our opponents are in possession
of all three parts of the code
and here are we
while the Bank of England plates
pass into their possession
Cheer up, old fellow, cheer up
As Dr. Samuel Johnson once said
"There's no problem
the mind of man can set
that the mind of man cannot solve"
What's that, old fellow?
Oh, just quoting Dr. Samuel Johnson
He said "There is no"–
Thank you, Watson, thank you
Leaving the front reception room
we come into the main hall
where Dr. Johnson was in the habit
of passing through
to have his meager meals
in the dining on opposite
in company with his friend and biographer
James Bosswald
We will now pass up the stairway
which remains in its natural wood finish
just as it was
when the good doctor was here
The framed etching on the wall
Is believed to have been
presented to Dr. Johnson
by the distinguished painter
Sir Joshua Reynolds
I've been told here that that picture
was given in by Mrs. Thrail
and it's definitely not a Reynolds
Is that important, my dear?
Oh, I'm sorry
Oh
This way, ladies and gentlemen
please this way
Move along children, move along
The secretary's not on this floor
Patience, Hamid
I have a feeling–
My dear Col. with Sherlock Holmes
out of the way what could go wrong?
And here we have the gallant library
in which Dr. Johnson
wrote his famous dictionary
and in which you will see also
many of the great man's books
and other items of interest
Step forward, ladies and gentle–
please step forward
Standing in the corner is the secratary
which contains many of the original works
by the literary genius
On this table, Dr. Johnson's cat Hodge
used to sleep while his master worked
The strange thing about this cat
ladies and gentlemen
was it's love of oysters
They do say that the dear doctor
often went hungry
To find the cat that delicacy
What a pity, hmm
Now we will visit the Grey Room
which is immediately below us
in which you will see the very bed
in which Dr. Johnson died
What did he die of?
Gout
Just gout
This way, ladies and gentlemen
mind the steps, please
Your keys
Third shelf up
♪ (dramatic music) ♪
The knife
Gentlemen, the Bank of England plates
Well, Mrs. Courtney
so we meet again
No, I shouldn't do that
if I were you, Col. Cavanaugh
I must congratulate you, Mr. Holmes
You're far more clever than I thought
Thank you, Mrs. Courtney
Praise from you is indeed gratifying
I shall always cherish the memory
of your flattering words
Memory?
Oh, thank you
And now I have a most
regrettable task to perform
(gunshot)
Holmes!
Coming, Holmes!
Holmes
You alright?
perfectly, thank you, old fellow
but I think this gentleman on the floor
requires some medical attention
we will see that he looks his best
you know, when he's hanged
Take them in charge
Hmm, a brilliant antagonist
It's a pity her talents
were so misdirected
Will you see
that these plates are returned
to the Bank of England, Inspector?
I still don't understand
how you solved it, Mr. Holmes–
It's entirely due to Dr. Watson
He gave me the clue when he mentioned
Dr. Samuel Johnson
Well, congratulations, Doctor
Oh, thank you, Inspector
I don't think I could have
done it entirely
without Mr. Holmes's help, you know
(laughter)